Good morning everybody, today's דף נד Daf Nun Dalet and we're dealing
with how the sort of the מזבח Mizbeach was missing most of
the base, the protruding part of the base, I should say, of
the east and the southern southern part because according to the גמרא
Gemara that part was in the portion of יהודה Yehuda and the
idea was the whole altar had to be in the portion of
בנימין. Binyamin. So this little thing, יהודה Yehuda was basically from the
east going all the way ending at the מזבח. Mizbeach. So the
actual, so ירושלים Yerushalayim was יהודה, Yehuda, but the actual place of
the מקדש Mikdash proper—actually that's not true because יהודה Yehuda included it
was a part of the actual מקדש Mikdash proper, not just the
הר הבית, Har Habayit, but actually the עזרה. Azarah. The 22 אמות:
Amot: 11 אמות Amot for where the ישראל Yisrael stood, 11 אמות
Amot for the כהנים. Kohanim. So actually that part was in יהודה
Yehuda as well. But when it got up to the מזבח, Mizbeach,
the altar, that started בנימין Binyamin and then that included the place
of the קודש Kodesh and the קודש הקודשים Kodesh Hakodashim and so
on. But יהודה Yehuda protruded a little bit into the east and
into the south so that right at right around the altar. So
because you wanted the whole altar in the portion of בנימין—why Binyamin
is that so important? I because of their דרשה drasha of the
פסוק, pasuk, I really don't know, we'll see in a minute a
slightly different interpretation. Anyway, that part did not have a protruding base.
So that's where we left off yesterday. Okay, so let's continue now.
So the גמרא Gemara says as following. It says דף נד עמוד
א. Daf Nun Dalet Amud Aleph. מיתיבי, Meitivei, three lines from the
top. I'll ask you on this idea that there was a portion
of the of the base that did not protrude. עולת העוף כיצד
היא נעשית? Olat Ha-of keitzad hee na'aseit? How would you do the
עולת העוף, Olat Ha-of, the bird עולה? olah? The bird עולה olah
was done at the top of the altar and it was done
at the first corner that the כהן Kohen hit. Okay, so it
was done right here at the southeast corner. All right, so it
would have been done like right here, like this is whatever, anyway,
this would have been the southeast corner right opposite where there was
no base below. All right, so how would you do it?
כיצד היא נעשית? Keitzad hee na'aseit? היה מולק את ראשה ממול עורפה.
Hayah moleik es roshah mimul orpah. You would sever the head from
the back, you know, from the nape of the neck with the
כהן's Kohen fingernail, ומבדיל, u'mavdil, and you would completely sever, doesn't mean
necessarily the head would fall off, it means that you would cut
through both the trachea and the esophagus, וממצה את דמה על קיר
המזבח, u'mematzeh es dammah al kir hamizbeach, you would squeeze out the
blood against the wall of the altar. Okay, against the wall of
the altar. Fine, that's what you do for an עולת העוף. Olat
Ha-of. ואי אמרת לא היה לו יסוד באוירא בעלמא הוא דקעביד? Ve'ee
amrat lo hayah lo yesod b'avira b'alma hu d'ka'avid? So if there
was no יסוד, yesod, how could he be squeezing out the blood
if it's in mid-air? Now, it's not literally in mid-air, but what
it means is it's being squeezed out at this corner and below
it there's no base. And our assumption is, well our assumption is
that other than the חטאת, chatat, our assumption is that any application
of blood, right, has to be opposite a base below. And so
here, how could that be? You know, so it's there—otherwise we say
that the blood of a normal עולה olah goes at the other
corners, but if this is up here opposite this corner, how do
you do it if there's no base below? That's the גמרא's Gemara
question. It assumes that that's not possible. Okay. So now,
of course רש"י's Rashi question is: what bothers the גמרא? Gemara? Because
since the כהן Kohen was at the top part of the altar
and the כהן Kohen was standing here, okay, the blood would actually
have a place to hit. It wouldn't be flowing in mid-air. It
would hit the סובב, soveiv, it would hit the roundabout, right? So
that's true, but because the red line was one אמה ammah below
the roundabout,
technically
speaking, you could do a—it's very funny, because a חטאת chatat could
only be up on these corners, actually although we had a discussion
whether it could be the entire length the entire height down. Okay,
but let's assume that a חטאת chatat could only be on those
corners and that's a debate of תנאים. Tannaim. But let's assume that
a חטאת chatat could only be on those corners. But the עולת
העוף Olat Ha-of was not on those corners, the עולת העוף Olat
Ha-of was anywhere at the top part of the altar. And that
would be that the כהן Kohen actually could do it in this
אמה ammah at the bottom section, you know, so above, but
it's still the top half?
It's the top half, but it's the bottom section, the bottom five
אמות. amot. And if so, if he did it up here fine,
it would hit the סובב, soveiv, it would hit the walk around.
But if you're going to do it here, is the גמרא's Gemara
bothered, above the red line, but in the bottom section of of
it, okay, then if the blood runs down and there's no base
for it to hit below and the גמרא Gemara assumes that that's
not possible, that the stuff would just run down without there to
be a base to catch it.
So it's וממצה את דמו אל קיר המזבח, u'mematzeh es dammo el
kir hamizbeach, which
means it's supposed to go on the wall. I understand, but this
is a גמרא's Gemara concept, that the same way the זריקת הדם
zrikas hadam requires there to be a יסוד yesod below, the squeezing
out of the blood of the עולת העוף Olat Ha-of requires there
to be some some base. The funny thing is, and this is
what תוספות Tosafot is about, is that רש"י Rashi understands that it's
not necessarily a הלכה halacha in יסוד, yesod, there's a הלכה halacha
about that it can't just be flowing in the air and having
the
ground. And we'll see from the גמרא's Gemara answer as well, for
רש"י Rashi it's not a concept of יסוד, yesod, it's a concept
of the blood has to have something to hit. Now that really
sharpens Michael's question. It's one thing to say, okay, the גמרא Gemara
until now has been assuming that all the blood has to be
כנגד היסוד, keneged hayesod, even if, you know, wherever you do the
זריקת הדם zrikat hadam there has to be a יסוד yesod below.
But why here is it not specifically a concept of יסוד, yesod,
why is it a concept of something to hit? And let's just
see the answer and you'll appreciate that that's at least the way
רש"י Rashi reads the גמרא, Gemara, that's what's bothering the גמרא. Gemara.
Just so he could stand on the סובב sovev and then do
it? Yes, right.
The כהן, Kohen, he could stand here and reach his hand down
and do that. That's what I was gonna say. I mean, yes.
I mean, it's true, it would be a little, it would require
a little dexterity. But yeah, you could stand and go below your
feet and squeeze it out. Okay, so let's see what the גמרא's
Gemara answer is. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק Amar Rav Nachman Bar
Yitzchak אימא הכי התנו eima hachi hitnu אויר דבנימין וקרקע דיהודה. avir
deBinyamin vekarka deYehuda. Okay, so he says that, you know what,
one minute, did
I skip a line?
No. So he says no, this was the condition, this was the
agreement. The agreement was the air space was בנימין Binyamin and the
floor space was יהודה. Yehuda. So as long as בנימין, Binyamin, as
long as this was in בנימין's Binyamin air space even though, you
know, even though it was not going to somehow, you know, hit
the ground here, this ground was יהודה, Yehuda, but the air space
above it was בנימין. Binyamin. So the blood, the blood would be
squeezed out over בנימין's Binyamin air space. So it sounds like that
that the problem isn't even that it has to hit something. It
sounds like that the problem is is that if you're saying all
the עבודה avoda of the מקדש Mikdash has to be, right, and
now maybe this is again not exactly how רש"י Rashi because we'll
tell you what רש"י Rashi inserts in this גמרא Gemara in a
minute, if you say all the עבודה avoda of the מקדש Mikdash
has to be in the space of בנימין, Binyamin, then you understand
the problem. The problem is not so much a problem of יסוד,
yesod, the problem is when the blood is hitting the sides of
this altar, if it's hitting right here at this edge, you with
me? Right, so that's and we assume that this space here right
below where the יסוד yesod would have protruded is now the, is
now that ground is יהודה's Yehuda space, and we assume the air
space is יהודה's Yehuda space, so the blood is being placed in
יהודה's Yehuda air space. You sort of see that? Right? Anywhere else,
right, you know the blood goes here, so that's not יהודה's Yehuda
air space, if it was up here then it's above it's one
אמה amah inserted if it's on the top section of the altar,
but if it's at the bottom section and at this corner, the
blood is is being put in יהודה's Yehuda air space. So the
מזבח mizbe'ach isn't in יהודה's Yehuda air space, but the blood is
in יהודה's Yehuda air space. So that was the question. It wasn't
so much a question of a יסוד yesod to read it this
way, it was a question of whose air space, whose zone was
the blood being placed in? And the answer was yes, even though
the ground, you know, יהודה Yehuda sold their air rights.
Okay, one of the earliest examples!
Even though the ground, even though the ground is יהודה, Yehuda, the
air rights were בנימין, Binyamin, so the blood was in בנימין's Binyamin
air space. Anyway, but if you look at רש"י, Rashi, that's basically
the answer we have in the גמרא. Gemara. But if you look
at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says the following: אומר כך התנו Omer
kach hitnu about 10 lines down, רש"י Rashi says ואיכא למימר ve-ika
lemeimar מלמעלה מג' דלאו קרקע הוא, milamala mi-gimmel delav karka hu, three
three טפחים tfachim off the ground because three טפחים tfachim within the
ground is connected to the ground, עשו כמין בליטה קטנה asu kemin
belita ktana כנגד אותו קרן keneged oto keren לקבל בה דם lekabel
ba dam עולת העוף olat ha'of שלא יפול לארץ shelo yipol la'aretz
וקיר מזבח מיקרי ve-kir mizbe'ach mikri אבל אל יסוד לא מיקרי aval
el yesod lo mikri להכשיר הקרן למתן דמים lehachshir hakeren lematan damim
הצריכין להינתן כנגד היסוד. hatzrichin lehinatein keneged hayesod. So what רש"י Rashi
now adds to this is, which is not in the גמרא, Gemara,
which is רש"י Rashi says what they would do is they would
put out a little protrusion here,
just on that one
corner, just right here at this corner, so that when the blood
ran down, it would not hit the ground. Now, but what רש"י
Rashi says now, רש"י Rashi is saying, what bothers תוספות Tosafot is
one minute, but like, do you need a יסוד yesod or you
don't need a יסוד? yesod? Because this ain't a יסוד, yesod, okay?
And if that was a יסוד, yesod, do the זריקה zrika of
the דם dam of the עולת העוף olat ha'of here. So רש"י
Rashi seems to be, I mean רש"י Rashi is saying is is
that the compromise, this isn't a יסוד, yesod, so the זריקה zrika
of the blood of the עולה olah has to be at the
opposite corners because that needs a יסוד. yesod. This doesn't need a
יסוד. yesod. So if it doesn't need a יסוד, yesod, why do
you need a protrusion to catch the blood? So what it seems
to be saying is is that not only does the blood have
to be hitting here the and be in the air space of
בנימין, Binyamin, but if the blood were to run down and hit
the ground, and when it would hit the ground, it would hit
the ground of יהודה, Yehuda, that somehow would be a problem. I
don't know why that would be a problem, the עבודה avoda would
be done when it hit the blood here, but somehow for רש"י,
Rashi, it's important that none of the blood go into יהודה's Yehuda
zone. So רש"י Rashi adds to the גמרא Gemara that there was
a little protrusion to catch the blood. Okay, but that's not in
the גמרא Gemara itself. It seems from the גמרא Gemara and certainly
רש"י Rashi says that doesn't make it a יסוד. yesod. So it
seems that what really bothers the גמרא Gemara is that the עבודה
Avodah would be done in the airspace of יהודה, Yehudah, and the
answer is it was the airspace of בנימין. Binyamin. Okay, fascinating little
discussion there, long תוספות Tosafos to figure that out too. So now,
yeah, because of
the problem, theoretical problem, he's inventing a new part of the רש״י.
Rashi. Yeah, I know, quite interesting, isn't it?
I don't know what to say, that's why you got a תוספות
Tosafos that argues on it. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. Now we have a position of לוי Levi that makes
the, that moderates this a little bit. מאי, Mai, where were we?
מאי לא הוה ליה יסוד? Mai lo hava lei yesod? What do
you mean there was no base? So רב Rav אמר amar בבנין,
be-vinyan, literally, there was no base, that there was no protruding base.
I mean, obviously there was a base, but it didn't protrude that
אמה, amah, that section. לוי Levi אמר amar בדמים. be-damim. No, no,
no. The architecture was normal. There was a protruding base all around,
same amount? All around. Yes, it looks normal, looks completely symmetrical. Thing
is because that was in יהודה's Yehudah space, they couldn't do any
of the blood work in over that base. It looks normal, they
just knew that was off limits, okay? And that's what, and therefore,
and that's what it was talking about. So everything else we've said
is the same. The קשיא kushya about the blood, the airspace belonging
to בנימין, Binyamin, the base though belonged, there was a base, it
belonged to יהודה, Yehudah, so don't do any עבודת הדם avodas hadam
over that base. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
רב Rav מתרגם metargem באכסנתיה יתבנא מדבחא. be-achsanteih yitbana madbecha.
The פסוק pasuk that we base this all on, which is, right,
which is, not בנימין, Binyamin, yeah, but before that פסוק, pasuk, it
was, yeah, ובין כתפיו שכן, u-vein kesafav shachen, right? בנימין זאב יטרף
בבקר יאכל עד, Binyamin zeev yitraf baboker yochal ad, ובין כתפיו שכן.
u-vein kesafav shachen.
God will dwell between his shoulders. So his Aramaic read of the
verse is the following. It's quite fascinating, just pause for a moment,
that this is not a literal translation, it is an Aramaic read,
and it's an Aramaic read of which we're inferring like what is
sort of the midrashic meaning that is going to tell us what
the actual halachic application of it would be. You know, so it's
interesting how תרגום Targum functioned as a type of a not just
translation but an authorized translation to communicate like the, you know, acceptable
normative rabbinic tradition around the verse, which is actually fascinating because if
you read our תרגום אונקלוס, Targum Onkelos, our תרגום אונקלוס Targum Onkelos
doesn't always follow הלכה. halacha. So anyway, רב Rav מתרגם, metargem, so
רב's Rav תרגום tirgum of this was באכסנתיה יתבנא מדבחא. be-achsanteih yitbana
madbecha. In his חלק, cheilek, in בנימין's Binyamin חלק, cheilek,
the מזבח mizbe'ach will be built. Okay, so that means that no
part of the altar was in יהודה's Yehudah portion, and there actually
the structure wasn't there in יהודה's Yehudah portion. לוי Levi מתרגם metargem
באכסנתיה be-achsanteih in his portion of בנימין's Binyamin portion
יתבני מקדשא. yitbanei mikdesha. The sanctuary will be built. Now what does
that mean? That sounds even more inclusive than, more expansive than the
מזבח. mizbe'ach. Okay, so no, the way he then reads it, his
תרגום tirgum of the תרגום Targum is מקום מקודש לדמים, makom mekudash
le-damim, that the place sanctified for blood. So yes, there could be
part of the altar in יהודה's Yehudah portion, but it was not
the place that was sanctified for or designated for where the blood
was going to go. So therefore the altar was there, the base
was there, but the blood would not go on that base. Okay.
And now we're going to go through a series of proofs to
prove whether actually structurally the base did not protrude or whether it
did protrude but they didn't put the blood there. Yes.
Yeah, I just want to understand that, but you know, so if
let's say the base protruded an אמה, amah, so how do they
build the ramp? So would it be like hollowed in an אמה?
amah?
So it could overlap? Excellent, that's going to be at the bottom
of the דף. daf. Oh, the, we're going to get to that.
Anybody who is an architect here or is an architect wannabe, just
wait till the bottom of the דף, daf, okay? Lego builder. What?
Lego builder, that's true. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, תא שמע, ta shema, come in here. יסוד היה מהלך על
פני כל הצפון ועל פני כל המערב.
Yesod hayah mehalech al
pnei kol hatzafon ve-al pnei kol hama'arav.
The base would go the entire extent of the north and of
the west, אוכל בדרום אמה אחת ובמזרח אמה אחת, ochel badarom amah
achas u-vamizrach amah achas, just like right this picture, it would go
the entire north and the entire west, and then it would חאפ
chap an אמה amah in the south and an אמה amah in
the east. Okay, and presumably that, and then the rest would not
have that protruding base. So that seems very explicitly like we've been
assuming, like רב, Rav, not like לוי, Levi, that the actual structure
would not be there. ובמזרח אמה אחת. u-vamizrach amah achas. מאי אוכל
נמי בדמים? Mai ochel nami be-damim?
So לוי Levi would say no, אוכל ochel means that that's the
part that would consume the
blood. So yes, the actual structure would go all the way around,
but only that portion of the base would be there for consumption
of blood. The other portion would not, you would not have the
blood above it. תא שמע, Ta shema, come in here. המזבח היה
שלשים ושנים על שלשים ושנים. Hamizbeach haya shloshim u-shnayim al shloshim u-shnayim.
It was 32 by 32. So according to this, it wasn't 32
by 32, it was 32 by 32... 31 almost, right? I mean
if you think about it, right, if you measured it at this
end it's 32 by 32. But if you actually try to figure
out the area of it, right, it's actually, it's 32 this way
and well I don't know what is it?
It's closer to 32 by 31, right? Is that right? If this
is 32
and this is 32 and then but actually it's
like because
if you sort of, yes, it's a little bit 32, but basically
it's this and this, right? Right, that's basically how it would look,
right? So basically and then this would, so it's really more like
31 by 32, right? If you were trying to estimate the area,
you would really do 31 times 32, not 32 by 32. Does
that make sense? This extra thing, right, is the extra אמה, amah,
right? So here is 31.
I'm sorry, so it didn't include that אמה? amah? That's what you're
saying?
Well, that's the point. Right, if you were measuring the area of
the base, the footprint, and you were to just ignore that extra
one little tiny אמה amah that protruded, a more accurate estimate of
the footprint is 31 by 32, not 32 by 32. So how
come it describes the base of the altar as 32 by 32?
Okay, that's the question. Why people looking in this stunned way? This
is not difficult, right? You're not getting this?
Why wouldn't it have said, couldn't you have said the same 31
by 31?
Well, if you're measuring just this corner, you say just these two
dimensions, you say 32 by 32. If you're measuring just these two,
you say 31 by 31. Right. But if I were to ask
you, Michael, approximately what is the footprint of the base? You would
have said 31 by 32.
It's 31 by 31 plus
the two little pieces.
Well, here, right, right, but no, but actually, but it goes,
whatever, it doesn't matter.
32 by 32, I'm not going to argue this point. 32 by
32 is not accurate. So the גמרא Gemara says, alright, תא שמע,
Ta shema, המזבח היה שלושים ושתים על שלושים ושתים. Hamizbeach hayah shloshim
u'shtayim al shloshim u'shtayim. הכא עסקינן מן הצד. Hacha askinan min hatzad.
Fine, we're not measuring it in all four directions. We're measuring these
two directions, the 32 by 32 directions, okay? Yes, it's not a
total accurate measure. Okay, תא שמע, Ta shema, come in here. נמצא
פורח אמה על יסוד ואמה על סובב. Nimtza porei'ach amah al yesod
v'amah al sovev. Now this is, I have to draw my nice
picture here like one thing's wonky. Okay, anyway, okay, so, so where
I guess we'll draw that, we'll take this one down.
That was your best one.
That was my best one. What can I tell you? Okay, so,
so here, okay, we're going to now, how did the ramp work?
Okay, so this again, this was three high, whatever, right? And then
you had five high, and then you had one. Okay, and the
base here was 32. Okay, and the ramp, the base of the
ramp, another גמרא Gemara will tell us is also 32. The base
of the ramp goes up like that. So the question is, but,
so there's another place it says that the base is 32 of
the ramp, the base of the מזבח mizbeach is 32.
And that was an אמה, amah, right? That corner on top?
This, yeah.
No,
I mean like the little corner, that's it.
And it says though that the combined footprint, the combined base is
62.
Now how did that happen?
62, you mean
64? Thank you, I do mean 62. Why? Because when we say
that the base is 32, we don't mean that the base at
the ground is 32. The base on the ground is 30, but
the base as the crow flies, the base measured from the top
is
32,
because it would, meaning not the base, whatever, the length measured from
the top is 32, because it would go in an אמה amah
here and in an אמה amah here and therefore the actual, right,
when the top here, if the כהן kohen started at the bottom
and walked to the top, he would have traversed 32 horizontal אמות.
amot. Okay? Because the top goes in two אמות amot beyond the
base because of the inset part of the מזבח. mizbeach. Okay? Now
that's all very nice. The problem is is that the ramp is
situated where? The ramp is
situated here, okay? So and you just told me that in the
south there's no actual protrusion. So if there's no actual protrusion, it
all works, but then you didn't have to say that the ramp
overhangs two אמות, amot, you could have actually built the base to
be 31 and have the ramp overhang only one אמה. amah. So
it all works, it's just when in describing this, why did you
say the ramp is 30 and it overhangs two אמות? amot? You
should have said the ramp was 31 and it overhangs one אמה.
amah. Okay, clear? So that's the question. So it says like this,
it says...
נמצא פורח, nimtza poreiach, the ramp is hovering, meaning like it extends
beyond its base, אמה על יסוד, ama al yesod, one אמה ama
over the base, and אמה על סובב ama al sovev and one
אמה ama over the walk around. So according to you, according to
רב, Rav, that there actually was no base at the protrusion at
the bottom, it should have just been a thirty-one base and hovering
one אמה. ama. So it says אימא כנגד אמת יסוד ועל אמת
סובב. eima keneged amat yesod ve’al amat sovev. Okay.
So
the actual words actually are the exact same almost.
It’s אמה על יסוד, ama al yesod, so it’s I don’t know,
anyway, רב Rav reads it—I’m just trying to see how it means
in the word, but right, what רש״י Rashi says it means is
that right, there was no protruding base here, but for whatever reason
the ramp, I guess also maybe to just represent—I don’t know why,
for symmetry purposes, the ramp could have gone thirty-one at the base,
but it didn’t go thirty-one at the base. The ramp actually the
base was only thirty and there was a and there was a
what do you call it an אמה ama of gap, a gap
of an אמה, ama, okay? And then structurally that wouldn’t be so
so good, but anyway, I don’t know, anyway what you did. Anyway
structurally there was that gap and
then it went all the way up and
then it went in all the way and it went in two
אמות. amot. So it did hover over one אמה ama over the
סובב sovev and one אמה ama over where the where the base
would have been. Okay. So it’s a pretty weak answer because because
because if this really were the structure the question is then just
build it all the way to the edge, right? Why would you
stop right before where the protrusion would have been? Okay, so I
don’t know, but anyway, that’s the answer. אימא כנגד אמת יסוד—not eima
keneged amat yesod אמה על יסוד ama al yesod but all right,
the keyword here is כנגד, keneged, כנגד אמת יסוד. keneged amat yesod.
It would hover over the אמה ama where the יסוד yesod should
have been, okay? But there was no actual יסוד yesod there. Fine.
תא שמע, ta shema, come in here, דתני לוי, detani Levi, לוי
Levi taught. Now we get to actually how they would do it
Michael. And Michael’s gonna be very interested in this too because everybody
wants to know, right, whenever you go on those, you know, the
הר הבית Har Habayit tours, they always teach, not the הר הבית,
Har Habayit, I’ve never been on a הר הבית Har Habayit tour,
the but the whatever the wall tours, you know, they always get
you to that place inside where they show you this big stone
and they say, how much do you think this stone weighs? It’s
like twenty feet long, whatever it weighs one hundred tons, I forget
how much it weighs, nobody knows how they were able to move
it up here. Anyway, so the question is how were they able
to build the מזבח, mizbeiach, right, this perfect thing, thirty-two, thirty, whatever.
What did they do, take a big stone and carve it? But
you’re not supposed to carve stones, right? So let’s take a look.
So it says like this, תא שמע דתני לוי, ta shema detani
Levi, כיצד בונין את המזבח. keitzad bonin et hamizbeiach. Now this is
לוי Levi himself actually taught this ברייתא, braita, which
because
לוי Levi might explain why לוי Levi has the position he does,
because this ברייתא braita is going to indicate that it was exactly
symmetrical, which is exactly לוי’ס Levi’s position, that it did protrude on
all sides. כיצד בונין את המזבח, keitzad bonin et hamizbeiach, how would
they bring it? מביאין מלבן שהוא שלשים ושתיים על שלשים ושתיים. mevi’in
malben shehu sheloshim ushtayim al sheloshim ushtayim. They would bring a like
a form—what’s it called like a like a mold, right, you know
a thing like a right some type of a frame, okay, that
would be thirty-two by thirty-two, like רש״י Rashi says sort of made
out of wood planks, okay, thirty-two long, one אמה ama high, okay,
so it would exactly be like a wood plank square thirty-two by
thirty-two, שהוא שלשים ושתיים על שלשים
ושתיים וגובהו אמה, shehu sheloshim ushtayim al sheloshim ushtayim vegohvo ama, and
an אמה ama high, ומביא חלוקי אבנים מפולמות, umevi chilukei avanim mefulamot,
they would bring like little, you know, rocks that were pebbles, well,
right, it’s gonna say they could have been bigger, that were wet,
moist, I guess that would make them better for adhering, and also
אבנים שלמות, avanim sheleimot, exactly, it would not be ones that you
had to be concerned that were somehow been chiseled. They were completely
whole, they were just taken from the ground. בין גדולות בין קטנות,
bein gedolot bein katanot, whether big or small. So you would have
you’d fill it through you’d fill it up with pebbles or small
stones. ומביא סיד וכוניא וזפת, umevi sid vechunya vezefet, you take plaster
and כוניא chunya some type of a lead, like a molten lead,
which would give it like I guess a hardening, וזפת vezefet and
tar, וממחה umemache and you sort of like stir it all together,
ושופך veshofech and you pour the cement into the stones
essentially. That’s how you would make it, so it really would be
a cement altar. וזהו מקום יסוד, vezehu mekom yesod, and that would
be the base, okay? וחוזר ומביא מלבן שהוא שלשים אמה על שלשים
אמה, vechozer umevi malben shehu sheloshim ama al sheloshim ama, then you
would do another another form of thirty by thirty, וגובהו חמש אמות,
vegohvo chamesh amot, right, and it would be five high, ומביא חלוקי
אבנים וכו׳, umevi chilukei avanim vechulei, וחוזר ומביא מלבן שהוא עשרים ושמונה
על עשרים ושמונה, vechozer umevi malben shehu esrim veshmonah al esrim veshmonah,
then you go in another אמה ama on each side, so it
goes from thirty-two to thirty to twenty-eight, because you’re in inserting an
אמה ama on each side, וגובהו ג׳ אמות, vegohvo gimmel amot, it’s
three high, ומביא חלוקי אבנים וכו׳, umevi chilukei avanim vechulei, והוא מקום
המערכה, vehu mekom hama’aracha, and at the top of that, that would
be where the fire would be. וחוזר ומביא מלבן שהוא אמה על
אמה, vechozer umevi malben shehu ama al ama, ומביא חלוקי... And you
get an אמה amah. על אמה amah על אמה cube, a cubic
אמה. ומביא זפת וקוניא ומחה ושף וזהו קרן. u-mevi zefet ve-konya u-macha
ve-shaf ve-zehu keren. And that's how you would then create the horns.
One would wonder how, like, did they do this in a way
in which, like, I guess the cement would sort of, would settle.
I'm trying to think as they did one portion on the next,
would the cement, how would it like adhere? Like how would you
get the tight adhering of the next section on top? I guess
as you're pouring the cement, it's, it's adhering to the part below
it. Anyway, וזהו קרן, ve-zehu keren, וכן לכל קרן וקרן. ve-chen le-chol
keren va-keren. Now, bottom line though is, what do you see? You
have the base was 32 by 32. It was an actual structure
of a full 32 by 32.
Wait, what was the height of the מערכה? ma'aracha? I thought you
did that already by having that one that's three high. No, no.
It means that the מערכה ma'aracha would be on top of this.
The same way when they did the five, they said this is
the סובב. sovev. The insert is where they would do the walk
around. Then when it said they did the three, the stuff that's
going to be on the top of the three is going to
be the fire. The same way the stuff that's on the top
of the five.
No, no, והוא מקום המערכה. ve-hu mekom ha-ma'aracha. Right. That's what the
מערכה ma'aracha just where you put the wood. What's this חלוקי אבנים
chilukei avanim for?
No, no, no. That's just for, look at, etc. חלוקי אבנים chilukei
avanim etc. dot dot dot. Okay,
then they poured in the cement, etc., etc. And then the whole
thing, that's where the מערכה ma'aracha would be on top. Okay, so,
okay. וזהו קרן, ve-zehu keren, וכן לכל קרן וקרן. ve-chen le-chol keren
va-keren. וכי תימא. ve-chi teima.
So now we've got the base is 32 by 32, which supports
לוי. Levi. And anyway, this is a ברייתא braita from that לוי
Levi taught. וכי תימא דגייז ליה, ve-chi teima de-gaiz lei, ah,
maybe you make a base of 32 by 32 and then you
chisel out an אמה inset, you know, on each side so you
actually then come in and you chop it out. So no, אבנים
שלמות כתיב, avanim shelemot ketiv, but it says whole stones. So you're
not allowed to chisel them. So דמחצי מידי מתויה, de-machis midi mi-tusei,
no, so here's how you do it. You use a frame of
32 by 32, but then you insert in the frame, okay, a
little, like, like a piece of wood.
Oh, ואחר כך שקיל ליה, ve-achar kach shakil lei,
and then you take that out, right? Right. So what you do
is you make a frame like that and then you insert, you
put in the frame some type of a piece of wood that's
like an, you know, that goes around those two sides and then
you pour everything in and it doesn't go into where that wood
insert is and then it sort of, it, it hardens and then
you take out your wood insert. Okay. So דמחצי מידי מתויה ושקיל
ליה. de-machis midi mi-tusei ve-shakil lei. Now, if you look at תוספות,
Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot asks the obvious question. Little תוספות, Tosafot, דגייז ליה.
de-gaiz lei.
תוספות Tosafot תימא מעיקרא ליהוי מלבין בנין זה. teima me-ikara le-havei malbin
binyan zeh. Why do you have to make a, a square מלבין
malbin and put an insert in it? Make a shape that's exactly
the shape that you want. So I don't know the answer to
that one. Okay. Okay. So then the גמרא Gemara says דאי לאו
תימא הכי, de-ei lav teima hachi, because if you don't say that
they use these types of inserts,
we're going to have a problem with how it describes the corners,
the horns. Why are we going to have a problem with how
it describes the horns? אמר רב כהנא, amar Rav Kahana, אבנים של
קרנות חלולות היו. avanim shel kranot chalulot hayu.
The actual stones that they used at the horns, those were actually,
you know, porous. The way רש"י Rashi explains it is that there
were holes, you know, it wouldn't just be you would put the
blood at the corner, on the corner and they, the blood would
just stay there. רש"י Rashi actually says that there were like little
holes into, in the, in those horns and the inside of the
horn was hollow, so that when you would apply the blood to
the horn, the blood would go into the holes and into the
hollow of the horn. Okay. Where it would go after that, I
don't know. Maybe all the way down. So anyway, so how you
know חלולות היו chalulot hayu that they were hollow? דכתיב ומלאו כמזרק
כזויות מזבח, de-chtiv u-mal'u ke-mizrak ke-zaviyot mizbe'ach,
and it will be filled like a, like a, you know, like
a funnel or a, you know, like the corners of the, of
the altar. So it has to be like something that basically is
a container, is, you know, a basin, a container, so it had
holes and it would actually collect the blood inside the hollow. So,
so how'd they do that? הכא נמי אבנים שלמות אמר רחמנא, hacha
nami avanim shelemot amar Rachmana, it says full stones. What are you
going to do, drill a hole in it? How did they make
that happen if they just did it by pouring plaster into this
mold? אלא דמחצי מידי מתויה ושקיל ליה. ela de-machis midi mi-tusei ve-shakil
lei.
So it must mean within this mold of one by one by
one for the horn
they had an insert, and the insert allowed there to be a
hollow form once they poured in the plaster. רש"י Rashi explains there
were also little like sticks that were there so that there would
be holes. You know, I guess if you imagine, right, if this
was the form, you'd have like a whole insert into the form
itself that would create a hollow so it would just sort of,
the plaster would just be like at the edges, and then in
addition you would have רש"י Rashi says like little protruding sticks so
that the plaster wouldn't form around there. So when you removed the
protruding sticks, you actually would get holes that would feed into the
hollow on the inside. Okay. So הכא נמי דמחצי מידי מתויה ושקיל
ליה. hacha nami de-machis midi mi-tusei ve-shakil lei. Fine. Now,
so that's how it happened. So we have that, so we still
don't know the answer, was it that the actual altar extended and
they just didn't put the blood there or the, or the base
didn't extend in that portion. דרש רבא. darash Rava. רבא Rava now
explicates. מאי דכתיב, mai de-chtiv, what's meant by the verse, וילך דוד
ושמואל וישבו בניות ברמה. va-yelech David ve-Shmuel va-yeshvu be-Nayot ba-Ramah. דוד ושמואל
David ve-Shmuel went and they dwelt in נויות. Nayot. Shmuel lived and
they were sitting in רמה *Ramah* which is where שמואל Shmuel. *Shmuel*
lived and ועוסקין בנויו של עולם *v'oskin b'noyoshel olam* and what they
were doing is they were learning הלכות בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash *Hilchos
Beis Hamikdash* and they were involving themselves in the questions of the
beauty, the most beautiful place of the world, of the place of
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash *Beis Hamikdash*. They were trying to figure
out where is it that the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. *Beis Hamikdash*
needs to be built. Okay so בנויו של עולם *b'noyoshel olam*. אמרי
Amrei, כתיב *Amri ktiv*. They said look the verse says וקמת ועלית
אל
המקום אשר יבחר השם *V'kamta
v'alita el hamakom asher yivchar Hashem*. You should rise up and go
to the place that God has chosen. מלמד שבית המקדש גבוה מכל
ארץ ישראל *Melamed sheBeis Hamikdash gavoah mikol Eretz Yisrael*. So the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash *Beis Hamikdash* has to be on the highest place
because it says if you have something that you don't know and
you need to find out you should rise up and go to
the place. So if it's saying wherever you are in ארץ ישראל
*Eretz Yisrael* it says you should rise up and go rather than
reading that literally and geographically, not metaphorically, it means that the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash *Beis Hamikdash* will always be at a higher elevation.
Okay? וארץ ישראל גבוהה מכל הארצות *V'Eretz Yisrael gavoah mikol ha'aratzot*. That's
רש"י *Rashi* says parenthetical that ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael* is higher than
other lands. That's not relevant for this discussion. Anyway it's fascinating the
way the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* interprets this literally and not metaphorically. לא
הוו ידעי דוכתיה היכא *Lo havu yad'ei duchteih heicha*. So let's try
to figure out where is the highest elevation in the whole land.
So if we were doing it we'd say oh no problem let's
just go to Google Earth and go ahead and get a topographical
map, boom, we can find it out in two minutes. Okay they
didn't have Google Earth instead they had ספר יהושע Sefer Yehoshua *Sefer
Yehoshua*. So אייתו ספר יהושע Yehoshua *Aitu Sefer Yehoshua*. They brought the
book of יהושע Yehoshua *Yehoshua* and they read as it described the
boundaries of ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*. ובכולהו כתיב וירד ועלה הגבול ותאר
הגבול *Uv'chulho ktiv vayered v'ala hagvul v'ta'ar hagvul*. When it described how
to draw the boundary it said the boundary goes up here and
it goes down here and it circumvents here and so that's when
it describes all the boundaries of the שבטים *Shevatim*. בשבט בנימין Binyamin
*B'shevet Binyamin* but when it got to the tribe of בנימין Binyamin
*Binyamin* it says ועלה כתיב וירד לא כתיב *V'ala ktiv vayered lo
ktiv*. It says here's where the boundary goes up but it never
says here's where the boundary goes down. The problem is it's not
true. It does say by בנימין Binyamin. *Binyamin* here where the boundary
goes down. So רש"י *Rashi* tries to make it better because what
רש"י *Rashi* says is that if you see where רש"י *Rashi* makes
a couple of points. I didn't check this in ספר יהושע *Sefer
Yehoshua* but anyway רש"י *Rashi* says right if here's whatever okay here's
my terrible version anyway of the land anyway רש"י *Rashi* says that
יהודה Yehuda. *Yehuda* basically's got the lower portion. This is יהודה Yehuda.
*Yehuda*. Okay and ירושלים Yerushalayim. *Yerushalayim* is here and רש"י *Rashi* points
out that when it gets to ירושלים *Yerushalayim* it actually says what
does רש"י *Rashi* say hold on one minute it says עד
ראש ההר על פני גיא בן הינום *Ad rosh hahar al
pnei Gei Ben Hinnom*. So רש"י *Rashi* says when it gets to
ירושלים
*Yerushalayim* as well it even describes it as it says ויעל עד
ראש ההר *Vaya'al ad rosh hahar* which is על פני גיא בן
הינום *al pnei Gei Ben Hinnom*. And if anybody knows right the
הר הבית Har HaBayit, *Har Habayis* is right by this valley called
גיא בן הינום *Gei Ben Hinnom* which is גיהנום *Gehennom*. Anyway so
there it says it goes up okay so it uses the word
ויעל *Vaya'al* right there around הר הבית Har HaBayit *Har Habayis* and
then רש"י *Rashi* says from that point on it never says ויעל
*Vaya'al* when it describes the rest of the boundary. It says it
goes ותאר *v'ta'ar*, it goes down, it never says ויעל *Vaya'al*. So
already that's an indicator that the high place here in ירושלים *Yerushalayim*
is this mountain right by גיא בן הינום *Gei Ben Hinnom*. רש"י
*Rashi* is adding this in. Okay and then when it describes בנימין
Binyamin.
*Binyamin*, so it's true that by בנימין Binyamin *Binyamin* when it describes
let's say the northern part of his boundary it might say ויעל
וירד *vaya'al vayered* or whatever okay, but so it's not true that
it never says וירד *vayered* by בנימין Binyamin *Binyamin* but when it
describes the southern part of his boundary it just says ויעל *vaya'al*
and it never says וירד *vayered*. Okay and when it says ויעל
*vaya'al* and it gets up to ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. So basically if you
read what it describes by יהודה Yehuda. *Yehuda*'s northern boundary around ירושלים
*Yerushalayim* that it says ויעל *vaya'al* when it gets to ירושלים *Yerushalayim*
and הר הבית *Har Habayis* and never says וירד *vayered* afterwards and
the same by בנימין *Binyamin*, all of that was pointing them to
the idea
that
right there in the southern part of בנימין *Binyamin* and the northern
part of יהודה Yehuda *Yehuda* and right at ירושלים *Yerushalayim* and right
at הר הבית *Har Habayis*, that's the high place cause that's where
it says ויעל *vaya'al*. Okay so then it says ועלה כתיב וירד
לא כתיב *V'ala ktiv vayered lo ktiv*. It says go up וירד
לא כתיב *vayered lo ktiv*. אמרי שמע מינה הכא הוא מקומו *Amri
shma mina hacha hu mekomo*. Oh this is where it is, it's
right here right in בנימין *Binyamin* right at the bottom of בנימין
*Binyamin* the top of יהודה Yehuda *Yehuda*. הכי הוא מקומו *Hachi hu
mekomo*. סבור למיבניה בעין עיטם *Savar l'mivneya b'Ein Eitam*. They wanted to
build it in עין עיטם Ein Eitam. *Ein Eitam* which is a
few kilometers away from ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. It's a place actually where they
have a wellspring, apparently there's an aqueduct from there that feeds ירושלים
*Yerushalayim*. I mean we don't have a place now that's called עין
עיטם Ein Eitam, *Ein Eitam* but they they suspect it's this other
place I forget the
name. 15 kilometers I think higher elevation than הר הבית. It's interesting.
So it's nearby and it's a little higher than הר הבית, okay.
So they thought maybe that's the place. Okay. דמדלי, Demidlei, that's a
little higher. אמרי, they said no,
נינחתי בפורסא, Nisasibe porsah, let's go down a little bit. Not to
be the highest place, sort of like the whole הר סיני Har
Sinai sort of model, right? Not the highest place, let's go down
a little bit, right, כדכתיב Kedichsiv ובין כתפיו שכן, uven ksefav shachen,
God dwells between בנימין's shoulders. And it doesn't say he dwells on
בנימין's head. So the space between the shoulders is the height but
not the highest height. There's gotta be like a good sermon in
there somewhere. Okay. ואיבעית
אימא, Ve'ibaiseima, that's one reason they assumed it was הר הבית and
not עין עיטם. Ein Eitam, If you want I could say, ואיבעית
אימא, Ve'ibaiseima, גמירי Gemiri דסנהדרין בחלקו דיהודה, deSanhedrin bechelko deYehuda, that we
know the סנהדרין Sanhedrin is in
יהודה. Yehuda, מחוקק, Mechokek, לא יסור שבט מיהודה ומחוקק מבין רגליו. lo
yasur shevet miYehuda umechokek miben raglav. מחוקק Mechokek is like the lawgiver.
Okay, so the סנהדרין Sanhedrin is in the portion of יהודה. Yehuda,
And we know here that the שכינה Shechinah is in the portion
of בנימין.
ושכינה בחלקו דבנימין. Veshechinah bechelko deBinyamin. ואי מדלינן ליה, Ve'im madlinan lei,
and if we raise it up and we put the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash in עין עיטם, Ein Eitam that's not going to be
right at the border of יהודה. This gets back to our earlier
theme, that the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. was exactly
divided between the portion of יהודה and the portion of בנימין. So
the portion of יהודה here, the לשכת הגזית Lishkas HaGazis was right
here before the עזרה. Azarah. It was right, so that was in
יהודה, and then a few steps later and you're in the portion
of בנימין with the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. But if you put
it in עין עיטם, עין עיטם is not near the border of
יהודה, so you're not going to get the סנהדרין Sanhedrin and the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, immediately juxtaposed.
ושכינה בחלקו דבנימין Veshechinah bechelko deBinyamin ואי מדלינן ליה, Ve'im madlinan lei,
if we raise it up, מתפלגי טובא, mitpalgi tuvei, it'll be very
distant. מוטב Mutav דנינחתי בפורסא, denisasibe porsah, we should lower it a
little bit. כדכתיב Kedichsiv ובין כתפיו שכן. uven ksefav shachen. Okay, and
that's how they figured out exactly where the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash,
goes.
ועל דבר זה נתקנא דואג האדומי. Ve'al davar ze niskanah Doeg HaEdomi.
דואג האדומי, Doeg HaEdomi, in the rabbinic mindset, he was the guy
that pointed out נוב עיר כהנים, Nov Ir Kohanim, got them all
wiped out or whatever. He was this enemy of דוד. David. But
in the rabbinic mindset, he was a big תלמיד חכם talmid chacham
and he was very jealous of דוד's David being such a תלמיד
חכם, talmid chacham, who, also in the rabbinic mindset, דוד David was
a big תלמיד חכם talmid chacham and so on. They were all
proto-rabbis. So, anyway, this is what דואג האדומי Doeg HaEdomi was so
jealous about that they were able to look into the פסוקים pesukim
and figure out where the בית המקדש would belong, they bested him
in that תורה Torah sort of point. כדכתיב, Kedichsiv, it says, כי
קנאת ביתך אכלתני, ki kin'as beisecha achaltani, the jealousy of Your house
consumed me. So the house is God's house. The jealousy of where
to understand God's house belong, that consumed me. וכתיב, Uchsiv, and then
the verse also says, זכור ה' לדוד, Zechor Hashem leDavid,
God remember for דוד David את כל ענותו, es kol anuso, all
of his
affliction, אשר נשבע לה', asher nishba laHashem,
if I will come באהל ביתי, be'ohel beisi, into the tent of,
דוד David said I won't enter into my own house until I
find the place of God. אם אבוא באהל ביתי אם אתן שנת
לעיני, Im avo be'ohel beisi im eten shenas le'einai, שנת לעיני, shenas
le'einai,
if I will give sleep to my eyes, לעפעפי תנומה, leafappai tenumah,
to my eyelids slumber, עד אמצא, ad emtza, I will not let
myself rest, עד אמצא מקום לה', ad emtza makom laHashem, until I
find a place for God. הנה שמענוה באפרתה, Hinei shemanua be'Efratah, we
have heard about this in אפרתה, Efratah, מצאנוה בשדי יער, metzanua bisde
ya'ar,
we have found, we have discovered it in the field of the
forest. So what does this mean? הנה שמענוה באפרתה, Hinei shemanua be'Efratah,
we heard it in אפרתה, Efratah, מצאנוה בשדי יער. metzanua bisde ya'ar.
באפרתה זה יהושע, Be'Efratah ze Yehoshua, we found it in the book
of יהושע because יהושע comes from
אפרת, Efrat, okay, דאתי מאפרים, de'asi me'Efrayim, I mean from אפרים. Efrayim.
מצאנוה בשדי יער, Metzanua bisde ya'ar, we found it in the forest,
זה בנימין, ze Binyamin, זאב יטרף, ze'ev yitrof,
he's a consuming wolf,
and therefore wolves are in the forest, wolves are in the forest
and there by looking in ספר יהושע and בנימין we realized it
was חלק בנימין chelek Binyamin and we discovered it. Very nice little
מדרש midrash about finding the בית המקדש. I should say the other
important idea that there is a very nice
religious point is the פסוק pasuk that it says
by the בית המקדש. What does it say? It
says
לשכנו תדרשו ובאת שמה, lishichno tidreshu uvassa shammah, you should seek out
God's place and come there and go there. So that's obviously the
פשט pshat of the פסוקים pesukim means there's a place of God
and people are like on a pilgrimage. But why do you have
to seek it out? If you know where it is, you just
go there. So the גמרא, so
there's a מדרש midrash that says that when you're trying to find
the place of the בית המקדש, you know, דרשהו על פי נביא,
darsheihu al pi navi, like first you have to try to figure
it out for yourself where the place of the מקדש Mikdash is,
and then the נביא Navi will come and confirm that that actually
is the place of the מקדש, Mikdash, you know, really like reflecting
this because it had דוד David and שמואל. Shmuel So it doesn't
actually say that שמואל then confirmed it with רוח הקודש, Ruach HaKodesh,
but that seems to be this point, like that it requires this
human effort. I mean the whole building of the בית המקדש, right?
The whole concept that if you want to create this place for
God, right, you know, God naturally is everywhere, right? בכל מקום אשר
אזכיר את שמי. Bechol makom asher azkir et shemi. So the idea
that God is going to concentrate, you know, His presence in a
particular place, you know, the whole half of the book of שמות
Shmos is about our human effort to create that place, you know,
and to create if we've exerted that effort to try to sanctify
and identify and build that place, you know, then God will sort
of like respond by His presence. So that sense that like actually
it was not supposed to be like just, you know, easy. Like
we're not going to tell you straight out it's in ירושלים. If
you want to create a place for God, you know, you have
to sort of דרשהו, darsheihu, you have to seek out that place
and then like the נביא Navi will confirm it and then that
will become the place that God will actually, you know, be present.
So that's actually very much reflected in this. Okay, now we just
got go to the next משנה, mishna, back to the normal קרבנות,
Korbanot, we did the חטאת Chatas and the עולה, Olah, and what's
left by the קדשי קדשים Kodesh Kodashim is the שלמים. Shlamim. Not
the שלמים, Shlamim, שלמים Shlamim normally is קדשי קלים, Kadshai Kalim, but
שלמי ציבור Shlamai Tzibur and the
אשמות. Ashamot. זבחי שלמי ציבור ואשמות. Zivchei Shlamai Tzibur VeAshamot. The שלמי
ציבור Shlamai Tzibur which are very few and the אשמות, Ashamot, those
are the remainder of the קדשי קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim. The אשמות Ashamot
are obviously a type of a sin-related thing and שלמי ציבור Shlamai
Tzibur is for like a חג. chag. Okay, אלו הן האשמות, Eilu
Hen HaAshamot, these are the אשמות. Ashamot. אשם גזלות, Asham Gezelot, somebody
steals and then swears falsely, not סתם stam stealing, swears falsely, they
bring an אשם. Asham. אשם מעילות, Asham Me'ilot, does someone does the
transgression of מעילה Me'ilah of benefiting from הקדש. Hekdesh. אשם שפחה חרופה,
Asham Shifcha Charufa, a man has intercourse with a maidservant who is
like half-freed, half-married, we'll see about that. אשם נזיר, Asham Nazir, a
נזיר Nazir became טמא Tamei and has to
restart
his נזירות. Nezirut. אשם מצורע Asham Metzora and a מצורע Metzora that
has to cleanse himself from his מצורע Metzora status. אשם תלוי Asham
Taluy and finally the suspended אשם, Asham, the אשם Asham that you
bring when you might have done something that you would bring a
חטאת Chatat but you don't know for sure. Okay, all these cases
are שחיטתן בצפון, Shchitatam BaTzafon, they are slaughtered in the north, וקבלתן
בכלי בצפון, VeKiblutam Bechli BaTzafon, and then they put, you know, you
catch it at the north, ודמן טעון שתי מתנות שהן ארבע, VeDamam
Te'un Shtei Matanot Shehen Arba, two that are four just like the
עולה. Olah. ונאכלות לפנים מן הקלעים Vene'echalot Lifnim Min Hakla'im is eaten
inside of the curtains in the עזרה, Azarah, וזכרי כהונה למאכל בכל
מאכל, Vezichrei Kehunah Lemachal Bechol Ma'achal, in any way, it doesn't have
to be roasted, it's not a קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, ליום ולילה,
LeYom VaLayla, the day and the following night, it could technically be
the whole night, but Rabbinically עד חצות Ad Chatzot until midnight. And
so we will pick up tomorrow with the אשמות. Ashamot.